Guide to the Hugh Adams Papers WLU.Coll.0373
Washington and Lee University, University Library Special Collections and Archives
Hugh Adams Papers
1857-1860
Washington and Lee University, University Library Special Collections and Archives
Adams, Hugh
WLU.Coll.0373
.25 Linear Feet
Box 1
Conditions Governing Access
Due to the physical condition of the Adams archive, under most circumstances, it is perferred that copies rather than original documents are used by researchers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Online Access
This collection has been digitized in its entirety and may be viewed online via WLU's Digital Archive.
Biographical / Historical
Hugh Adams (1793-1858) was a landowner, farmer, and slaveholder in the vicinity of Brownsburg, Rockbridge County, Virginia. He was a member and proponent of the American Colonization Society, the national organization promoting the emmigration of free African Americans to Liberia.
Custodial History
The archive was collected by Hugh Robert Bolen of Bustleburg, Rockbridge Co., Virginia. It was discovered amongst family papers by John Bolen, son of the collector.
Scope and Contents
The Hugh Adams Papers archive is comprised of approximately 75 documents concerning the emancipation of nineteen slaves of the Adams estate and their estate imposed emigration to Careysburg, Liberia. Adams was actively involved for many years with the American Colonization Society ( A.C.S.) which promoted and engaged in the emigration process of free or freed African-Americans to Liberia on the west African coast. Included in the archive is an original handwritten copy of the will of Hugh Adams. Within the will, Adams settles his estate and specifically outlines his plan for emancipating his slaves and for funding their imposed emigration. The archive also contains account documents for living expenses of nine of the nineteen freed slaves during the interim period between emancipation and their voyage to Liberia in May 1860.The surnames of the emancipated persons and families are Adams, Miles, Halliburton, Lewis, and Johnston or Johnson. Other noteworthy contents include an official Rockbridge County manumission document and two contracts detailing the purchase of enslaved husbands by their wives who were emancipated and funded by Adams' will. Other individuals whose names are found on documents within this archive include Rockbridge County lawyers Greenlee Davidson and David P. Curry, lawyers 'Gilkeson and McNutt', possibly of Augusta County, Virginia, Rockbridge County officials Samuel McDowell Reid, Charles Chapin, and David J. Whipple, estate executors A.M. Carson and Robert Hutcheson, and A.C.S. secretary Reverend William McLain. Click here to access the Hugh Adams Papers in WLU's Digital Archive.
Slaves -- Biography; Virginia -- Brownsburg; Free African Americans; Virginia -- Rockbridge County; Antislavery movements; Liberia -- Careysburg; Adams family; Lewis family; Miles family; Davidson, Greenlee; McLain, W. (William); Halliburton family; American Colonization Society; Curry, David P.; Reid, Samuel McDowell; Whipple, David J.; Chapin, Charles; Hutcheson, Robert; Carson, A. C.
- Control Folder (Box 1)
  General
  The control folder for the Hugh Adams Papers contains a physical folder list with descriptive information about contents, a transcription of Hugh Adams' will (1860), copies of online resources, including materials provided by the Library of Virginia, pertaining to the families and individuals formerly enslaved by Hugh Adams who emigrated to Liberia in May 1860.
- User copies (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  Will; Adams, Hugh
- Hugh Adams's Will, 1860; Adams, Hugh (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Scope and Contents
  In the will of Hugh Adams, he writes that he desires the emancipation of all his slaves upon his death.
  Will; Slavery -- Emancipation
- Court Document Pertaining to a Case Contesting Adams' Will, 1860 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Adams, Hugh
- Papers Pertaining to Adams' Slaves, 1859; 5 Item (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Slavery
  - Notes on "Adams Negroes" (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Invoice for A. M. Carson and R. S. Hutcheson, 1859-07-15 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letter from R. Hutcheson, 1859-03-26 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Invoice for A. M. Carson, 1860 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Receipt for R. Hutcheson from W. McLain, 1860-04-19 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence from Hugh Adams family about the estate, 1858-1859 (Box 1, Folder 4a)
- Papers Related to Business Conducted Between Adams and Hutchinson, 1878-1890; Adams, Hugh; 4 Item (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Invoice for R. Hutcheson from Wade, 1880-01-01 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Receipt from Adams & Lockridge to R. S. Hutcheson, 1890-12-04 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Receipt from Adams & Lockridge to R. S. Hutcheson, 1890-11-18 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Papers Related to the Living Expenses of Andy Adams, 1860-1870; 6 Item (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Adams, Andy
  - Invoice from McNutt for Andy, 1860 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Invoice from A. M. Carson for Andy, early 1859 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Invoice from A. M. Carson for Andy, late 1859 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Invoice from A. M. Carson for Andy, 1860-04-14 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Final Statement for Andy, 1860-04-19 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Final Receipt for Andy, 1860-04 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Papers Related to the Living Expenses of George Adams, 1860-1870; 1 Item (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Adams, George
  - Invoice from W. McLain for George, 1860-04 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Papers Related to the Living Expenses of Henry Adams, 1838-1860; 7 Item (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Adams, Henry
  - Invoice from A. M. Carson for Henry, 1859 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Invoice from Gilkeson & McNutt for Henry, 1860 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Invoice from A. M. Carson for Henry, 1859-07-01 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Invoice from A. M. Carson for Henry, 1860-04-14 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Invoice from Ward Bros. for Henry, 1860-04-18 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Final Receipt for Henry, 1860-04 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Papers Related to the Living Expenses of Isabella Adams, 1859-1860; 3 Item (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Adams, Isabella
  - Invoice from Gilkeson & McNutt for Isabella, 1859-12 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Final Receipt for Isabella, 1860-04 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Papers Related to the Living Expenses of Joshua Adams, 1859-1860; 6 Item (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Adams, Joshua
  - Invoice from A. M. Carson for Josh, 1859-07-01 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Invoice from A. M. Carson for Josh, 1860-04-14 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Invoice from Gilkeson & McNutt for Josh, 1860 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Final Statement for Josh, 1860-04-19 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Final Receipt for Joshua, 1860-04 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Certification and Declaration of Joshua Adams, 1860; 1 Item (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Emancipation Certificate for Joshua Johnson, 1860-04-02 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Papers Related to the Living Expenses of Mary Adams, 1860; 3 Item (Box 1, Folder 12)
  Adams, Mary
  - Invoice from Gilkeson & McNutt for Mary, 1860-03 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Final Statement for Mary, 1860-04-19 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Final Receipt for Mary, 1860-04 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Papers Related to the Living Expenses of Rose Adams, Reuben Lewis, and Their Daughter, Rose Adams, 1859-1860; 10 Item (Box 1, Folder 13)
  Rose and Rueben's daughter was two-years old at the time.
  Adams, Rose; Lewis, Reuben; Adams, Rose
  - Purchase Agreement, Rosa and Reuben, 1860-04-14 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Invoice 1 from A. M. Carson for Rosy, 1859 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Invoice 2 from A. M. Carson for Rosy, 1859 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Invoice from Gilkeson & McNutt for Rose, 1860-04 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Invoice from A. M. Carson for Rosey, 1860-04-14 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Final Statement for Rosa, 1860-04-19 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Summary of Boarding Charges, 1860-04-20 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Final Receipt for Rosa, 1860-04 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Invoice from Ward Bros for Reuben, 1860-04-19 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Contract between John Letcher and Robert Hutcheson for the sale of Rosa, 1856-04-06 (Box 1, Folder 13a)
- Papers Relating to the Living Expenses of Scylla Adams and William Halliburton, 1859-1860; 7 Item (Box 1, Folder 14)
  Adams, Scylla; Halliburton, William
  - Invoice from A. M. Carson for Scilla, 1859-07-01 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Final Receipt for Sylla Jane, 1860-04 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Final Statement for Sylla Jane, 1860-04 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Invoice from Gilkeson & McNutt for Scilla, 1860 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Invoice from A. M. Carson for Scylla, 1859 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Invoice from A. M. Carson for Scilla, 1860-04-14 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Receipt from Hamilton Easter & Co. for Wm. Halliburton, 1860-04-19 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Additional Items relating to Scylla Adams and William Halliburton, 1859-01-19-1861-04-01 (Box 1, Folder 14a)
  - Agreement between Andrew Patterson and Robert Hutcheson for the sale and emancipation of William "Bill" Halliburton, 1859-01-19 (Box 1, Folder 14a)
- Scylla Adams' Purchase Agreement for William Halliburton, 1860; Adams, Scylla; 1 Item (Box 1, Folder 15)
  William Halliburton was Scylla's husband.
  Halliburton, William
  - Purchase Agreement, Sylla Jane and Bill Haliburton, 1860-04-14 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Papers Related to the Living Expenses of Susan Adams, 1860; 2 Item (Box 1, Folder 16)
  Adams, Susan
  - Final Receipt for Susan, 1860-04 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Final Statement for Susan, 1860-04-19 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Papers Related to the Living Expenses of Andrew Miles, 1860; 2 Item (Box 1, Folder 17)
  Miles, Andrew
  - Invoice from Ward Bros. for Andrew Miles, 1860-04-19 (Box 1, Folder 17)